<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Cubadebate (English)</title>
	<atom:link href="http://en.cubadebate.cu/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu</link>
	<description>Cubadebate, Against Terrorism in the Media</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 18:11:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>es-ES</language>
		<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
		<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://wordpress.org/?v=3.8.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>STATEMENT BY THE CUBAN PRESIDENT</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/12/17/statement-by-cuban-president/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/12/17/statement-by-cuban-president/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 18:11:20 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cubadebate</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Cuban Five]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuba]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[USA]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=6394</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[As Fidel promised on June 2001,when he said: “They shall return!” Gerardo, Ramon, and Antonio have arrived today to our homeland. The enormous joy of their families and of all our people, who have relentlessly fought for this goal, is shared by hundreds of solidarity committees and groups, governments, parliaments, organizations, institutions, and personalities, who for the last sixteen years have made tireless efforts demanding their release. We convey our deepest gratitude and commitment to all of them.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="line-height: 1.5em"><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-4026" alt="Cinco heroes" src="/files/2013/04/Cinco-heroes.jpg" width="300" height="250" />(December 17, 2014)</span></p>
<p>Fellow countrymen,</p>
<p>Since my election as President of the State Council and Council of Ministers I have reiterated in many occasions our willingness to hold a respectful dialogue with the United States on the basis of sovereign equality, in order to deal reciprocally with a wide variety of topics without detriment to the national Independence and self-determination of our people.</p>
<p>This stance was conveyed to the US Government both publicly and privately by Comrade Fidel on several occasions during our long standing struggle, stating the willingness to discuss and solve our differences without renouncing any of our principles.</p>
<p>The heroic Cuban people, in the wake of serious dangers, aggressions, adversities and sacrifices has proven to be faithful and will continue to be faithful to our ideals of independence and social justice. Strongly united throughout these 56 years of Revolution, we have kept our unswerving loyalty to those who died in defense of our principles since the beginning of our independence wars in 1868.</p>
<p>Today, despite the difficulties, we have embarked on the task of updating our economic model in order to build a prosperous and sustainable Socialism.</p>
<p>As a result of a dialogue at the highest level, which included a phone conversation I had yesterday with President Obama, we have been able to make headway in the solution of some topics of mutual interest for both nations.</p>
<p>As Fidel promised on June 2001,when he said: “They shall return!” Gerardo, Ramon, and Antonio have arrived today to our homeland.</p>
<p>The enormous joy of their families and of all our people, who have relentlessly fought for this goal, is shared by hundreds of solidarity committees and groups, governments, parliaments, organizations, institutions, and personalities, who for the last sixteen years have made tireless efforts demanding their release. We convey our deepest gratitude and commitment to all of them.</p>
<p>President Obama’s decision deserves the respect and acknowledgement of our people.</p>
<p>I wish to thank and acknowledge the support of the Vatican, most particularly the support of Pope Francisco in the efforts for improving relations between Cuba and the United States. I also want to thank the Government of Canada for facilitating the high-level dialogue between the two countries.</p>
<p>In turn, we have decided to release and send back to the United States a spy of Cuban origin who was working for that nation.</p>
<p>On the other hand, and for humanitarian reasons, today we have also sent the American citizen Alan Gross back to his country.</p>
<p>Unilaterally, as has always been our practice, and in strict compliance with the provisions of our legal system, the concerned prisoners have received legal benefits, including the release of those persons that the Government of the United States had conveyed their interest in.</p>
<p>We have also agreed to renew diplomatic relations.</p>
<p>This in no way means that the heart of the matter has been solved. The economic, commercial, and financial blockade, which causes enormous human and economic damages to our country, must cease.</p>
<p>Though the blockade has been codified into law, the President of the United States has the executive authority to modify its implementation.</p>
<p>We propose to the Government of the United States the adoption of mutual steps to improve the bilateral atmosphere and advance towards normalization of relations between our two countries, based on the principles of International Law and the United Nations Charter.</p>
<p>Cuba reiterates its willingness to cooperate in multilateral bodies, such as the United Nations.</p>
<p>While acknowledging our profound differences, particularly on issues related to national sovereignty, democracy, human rights and foreign policy, I reaffirm our willingness to dialogue on all these issues.</p>
<p>I call upon the Government of the United States to remove the obstacles hindering or restricting ties between peoples, families, and citizens of both countries, particularly restrictions on travelling, direct post services, and telecommunications.</p>
<p>The progress made in our exchanges proves that it is possible to find solutions to many problems.</p>
<p>As we have reiterated, we must learn the art of coexisting with our differences in a civilized manner.</p>
<p>We will continue talking about these important issues at a later date</p>
<p>Thank you.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/12/17/statement-by-cuban-president/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Special appearance by Raul on the United States</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/12/17/special-appearance-by-raul-on-united-states/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/12/17/special-appearance-by-raul-on-united-states/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2014 14:57:07 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cubadebate</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Cuban Five]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuba]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Raúl Castro Ruz]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=6392</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Army General Raúl Castro Ruz, President of the State Council and Council of Ministers will address the Cuban people and the international public opinion this Wednesday 17 at noon to make an important announcement regarding relations with the United States. At 12:00 noon, the Cuban television and radio shall broadcast the address by the President, which will be broadcast by Cubavisión  Internacional, Radio Habana Cuba and digital media sites in the Island.  ]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="/files/2012/07/raul-castro-rusia.jpg" alt="Raúl Castro" width="300" height="250" class="alignleft size-full wp-image-3125" />Army General Raúl Castro Ruz, President of the State Council and Council of Ministers will address the Cuban people and the international public opinion this Wednesday 17 at noon to make an important announcement regarding relations with the United States.</p>
<p>At 12:00 noon, the Cuban television and radio shall broadcast the address by the President, which will be broadcast by Cubavisión  Internacional, Radio Habana Cuba and digital media sites in the Island.  </p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/12/17/special-appearance-by-raul-on-united-states/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The moment &#8216;unarmed civilian was shot dead by an Israeli sniper&#8217; as he desperately searched for his family (+ Video)</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/07/23/moment-unarmed-civilian-was-shot-dead-by-an-israeli-sniper-as-he-desperately-searched-for-his-family-video/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/07/23/moment-unarmed-civilian-was-shot-dead-by-an-israeli-sniper-as-he-desperately-searched-for-his-family-video/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2014 23:10:44 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cubadebate</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gaza]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Israel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Terrorism]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[War]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=6243</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is the harrowing moment a young Palestinian man was allegedly shot by an Israeli sniper in front of a camera crew helping him search for his family before being fatally shot again as he struggled to get up. The footage, which MailOnline can not independently verify, was captured by an activist from the pro-Palestinian International Solidarity Movement in the Shijaiyah neighbourhood of Gaza City. ]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div><a rel="nofollow" target="_blank" href="http://exbackgod.com/your-ex-still-wants-you.html"  title="Your Ex Still Wants You">Your Ex Still Wants You</a></div>
<p><a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2701043/The-shocking-moment-Palestinian-civilian-shot-dead-Israeli-sniper-lying-defenceless-floor-earlier-hit.html"  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">By Mail Online</a> This is the harrowing moment a young?Palestinian?man was allegedly shot by an Israeli sniper in front of a camera crew helping him search for his family before being fatally shot again as he struggled to get up. The footage, which MailOnline can not?independently?verify, was captured by an?<span>activist from the pro-Palestinian International Solidarity Movement in the Shijaiyah neighbourhood of Gaza City.?</span> Muhammad Abdellah claimed he and other ISM volunteers made their way into Shijaiyah on Sunday after the area came under prolonged and heavy bombardment from Israel, which claims the neighbourhood is a major source for Hamas rocket fire against its civilians. <div id="attachment_6249" style="width: 470px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-full wp-image-6249" alt="The harrowing footage was captured by Muhammad Abdellah. an activist from the pro-Palestinian International Solidarity Movement in the Shijaiyah neighbourhood of Gaza City." src="/files/2014/07/he-harrowing-footage-was-captured-by-Muhammad-Abdellah.jpg" width="470" height="523" /><p class="wp-caption-text">The harrowing footage was captured by Muhammad Abdellah. an activist from the pro-Palestinian International Solidarity Movement in the Shijaiyah neighbourhood of Gaza City.</p></div> <div id="attachment_6248" style="width: 470px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-large wp-image-6248" alt="He claimed that the ISM team came across a young Palestinian man, who told them he was looking for his family, and that they followed him in an attempt to help him find his relatives." src="/files/2014/07/he-harrowing-footage-was-captured-by-Muhammad-Abdellah.-an-activist-from-the-pro-Palestinian-International-Solidarity-Movement-in-the-Shijaiyah-neighbourhood-of-Gaza-City1.jpg" width="470" height="523" /><p class="wp-caption-text">He claimed that the ISM team came across a young Palestinian man, who told them he was looking for his family, and that they followed him in an attempt to help him find his relatives.</p></div> <div id="attachment_6247" style="width: 580px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-large wp-image-6247" alt="As the group tried to make their way across a heavily damaged area, shots suddenly rang out.The first sent the group scrambling for cover, but did not hit anyone, but the second hits the man in the green t-shirt." src="/files/2014/07/As-the-group-tried-to-make-their-way-across-a-heavily-damaged-area-shots-suddenly-rang-out.The-first-sent-the-group-scrambling-for-cover-but-did-not-hit-anyone-but-the-second-hits-the-man-in-the-green-t-shi-3-580x314.jpg" width="580" height="314" /><p class="wp-caption-text">As the group tried to make their way across a heavily damaged area, shots suddenly rang out.The first sent the group scrambling for cover, but did not hit anyone, but the second hits the man in the green t-shirt.</p></div> <div id="attachment_6246" style="width: 580px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-large wp-image-6246" alt="'Israeli soldier sniper hit him in his hip, so he laid down. And I started to ask him 'can you move?' Because if he can move, maybe he can roll around and go to the other place, but he said 'no, I cannot move, like my blood is going everywhere'." src="/files/2014/07/As-the-group-tried-to-make-their-way-across-a-heavily-damaged-area-580x315.jpg" width="580" height="315" /><p class="wp-caption-text">&#8216;Israeli soldier sniper hit him in his hip, so he laid down. And I started to ask him &#8216;can you move?&#8217; Because if he can move, maybe he can roll around and go to the other place, but he said &#8216;no, I cannot move, like my blood is going everywhere&#8217;.</p></div> <div id="attachment_6245" style="width: 580px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-large wp-image-6245" alt="Abdellah explained that he and the other ISM volunteers were unable to approach the young man, amid fears they would be targeted too.Then, the Palestinian was hit a second time as he lay on the ground." src="/files/2014/07/As-the-group-tried-to-make-their-way-across-a-heavily-damaged-area3-580x318.jpg" width="580" height="318" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Abdellah explained that he and the other ISM volunteers were unable to approach the young man, amid fears they would be targeted too.Then, the Palestinian was hit a second time as he lay on the ground.</p></div> <div id="attachment_6244" style="width: 580px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-large wp-image-6244" alt="'And that bullet, I guess it was in his heart or like or almost there, because he was like going and dying in front of our eyes,' the activist said." src="/files/2014/07/As-the-group-tried-to-make-their-way-across-a-heavily-damaged-area4-580x317.jpg" width="580" height="317" /><p class="wp-caption-text">&#8216;And that bullet, I guess it was in his heart or like or almost there, because he was like going and dying in front of our eyes,&#8217; the activist said.</p></div> <p><a href="http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/07/23/moment-unarmed-civilian-was-shot-dead-by-an-israeli-sniper-as-he-desperately-searched-for-his-family-video/"><em>Pinche aquí para ver el vídeo</em></a></p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/07/23/moment-unarmed-civilian-was-shot-dead-by-an-israeli-sniper-as-he-desperately-searched-for-his-family-video/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Innocence of Gerardo</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/opinions/2014/05/22/innocence-gerardo/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/opinions/2014/05/22/innocence-gerardo/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 19:14:29 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Ricardo Alarcón de Quesada</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Opinions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ricardo Alarcón de Quesada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuba]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuban Five]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gerardo Hernandez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=6153</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The meeting in London of the Commission of Inquiry on the case of the Cuban Five examined in depth the specific situation of Gerardo Hernández Nordelo and the infamous charge (Count 3 “conspiracy to commit murder”) lodged only against him. It forms the basis of his sentence, in which he must die two times in prison. He is falsely accused of having participated in the shoot-down of the two planes of the terrorist group that calls itself “Brothers to the Rescue.” ]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-2394" alt="Gerardo Hernández" src="/files/2011/12/gerardo-hernandez.jpg" width="300" height="250" />The meeting in London of the Commission of Inquiry on the case of the Cuban Five examined in depth the specific situation of Gerardo Hernández Nordelo and the infamous charge (Count 3 “conspiracy to commit murder”) lodged only against him. It forms the basis of his sentence, in which he must die two times in prison. He is falsely accused of having participated in the shoot-down of the two planes of the terrorist group that calls itself “Brothers to the Rescue.”</p>
<p>From a legal point of view, for it to have standing in a United States court, the deed in question had have had to occur in international airspace, outside of Cuban jurisdiction. Otherwise, no court of the United States would have been able to take it up.</p>
<p>That is why in the Miami trial the exact location of the incident was discussed at length, repeating what had taken place before in the Security Council of the United Nations and in the International Civil Aviation Organization (ICAO). In those discussions, the contradictions between the Cuban radar and those of the United States arose continuously. There is certainly a great deal to write about the U.S. data, for example, the delay of several months in handing it over, which forced a delay in the work of the ICAO and the suspicious destruction of some records, all of which is stated in the ICAO report.</p>
<p>In order to try to resolve the discrepancy in the radars, the ICAO asked the United States to submit the images from its space satellites, a request that was rejected in 1996. Washington also refused to permit the Miami Court to view them. For a long time now it has been opposing the repeated requests by the Center for Constitutional Law and Human Rights of California and has litigated in the Courts of that State in its effort to keep the images from being seen. Soon it will be 20 years of obstinate censorship.</p>
<p>Only the United States has been able to examine what its satellites filmed, but no one else is permitted to see them. Not the UN Security Council, nor the ICAO, nor the United States courts. Why?</p>
<p>There is only one answer. Washington knows that the incident occurred inside Cuba’s territorial waters, very close to the Havana coast and consequently, it never had legal jurisdiction over it. Since the satellite images are irrefutable proof of the Yankee lie nobody but the United States authorities will ever be able to see them.</p>
<p>But the issue is not whether the satellite images exonerate Gerardo. They were not necessary because to convict him the Prosecution had to prove that he personally participated in the incident, something totally absurd, impossible to sustain regardless of where the shoot-down of the invading planes occurred. That problem was and is for Washington.</p>
<p>A problem, because the images prove that the United States, its authorities and its courts had no right whatsoever to try an incident that took place outside its territorial jurisdiction. It should be pointed out, that according to the U.S. radars, the planes flew together the whole time in a southerly direction and at least one of them, according to the U.S.’s own version, had penetrated Cuban territory. Indeed, if one accepts the United States theory about the planes’ location, they were in the vicinity of the Cuban capital, very close to its most central and populous part. In a few minutes they would have flown over it and would have been able to cross the island to the southern coast.</p>
<p>This did not take place near the United States airspace, rather it was far below the 24th Parallel which demarcates the zones of aerial supervision of both countries. It was there, within the area under Cuban control where a good part of the flight transpired, southward toward Havana and ignoring the indications and warnings issued by the Air Traffic Control Center of our country.</p>
<p>In any case, Gerardo had absolutely nothing to do with the deed, no matter where it occurred. And the United States authorities knew that perfectly well.</p>
<p>According to the Indictment of September 1998, the FBI had identified Gerardo and knew the mission he was carrying out. From 1994 on they were viewing his communications with Cuba, more than two years before that incident which grievously affected the situation between both countries.</p>
<p>The mobs of the Batista-terrorist mafia called then for war in the streets of Miami. Meanwhile, according to what President Clinton wrote in his Memoirs, the White House was discussing a possible bombardment of Cuba. He opted to promote the Helms-Burton law, accompanied by bellicose threats. Can anyone believe that they would not act against Gerardo if he had been involved? They did nothing precisely because his innocence was clear to them.</p>
<p>It is also the reason they did not charge him when he was arrested together with his comrades in September 1998. In the initial indictment not one word is said about the event of February 24, 1996, nor is anything said about the plane shoot-down or related issues. They did not do that because the FBI, which possessed and had read the messages between Gerardo and Havana, knew he was innocent.</p>
<p>Count 3 (“conspiracy to commit murder”) was drawn up only against Gerardo. It was more than seven months after the arrest of the Cuban Five, when they were in solitary confinement — the infamous “Hole” — isolated from the world and where it was impossible to defend themselves. To that end the Prosecution presented a Second Superseding Indictment that — as the Miami press described it — was created in meetings openly carried out by the FBI, the Prosecution and the leaders of the terrorist groups.</p>
<p>It was an arbitrary accusation, fabricated top to bottom, with the sole objective of satisfying the criminals, inflaming the hatred against Gerardo and his comrades and guaranteeing beforehand the worst, most illegal and irrational convictions. Count 3 was the focus of the lawless and vulgar media campaign, promoted and financed by the Federal Government. Like a tsunami of lies, it slammed a defenseless community paralyzed by terror. It was five articles per day in the print newspapers, endless commentaries day and night on radio and local television, creating what the panel of judges in the 11th Circuit Court of Appeals in 2005 characterized as a “perfect storm” of hatred, prejudice and hostility.</p>
<p>A major part of the trial centered on Count 3. Inside and outside the courtroom, individuals linked to “Brothers to the Rescue” agitated and made strident statements that the local media amplified. They and the U.S.-paid “journalists” persecuted and besieged the members of the jury who complained to the judge. She, for her part, several times also complained to the Government, of course, to no avail.</p>
<p>In the courtroom, despite all this, the baseless lie of the Prosecution was defeated. The accusers, who were so effectively promoting hatred and prejudice against him, were unable to present one single proof to connect Gerardo to the events of February 24. Not a thing.</p>
<p>So overwhelming and obvious was its defeat that the Government did something highly unusual. At the end of the discussions, when the judge was about to issue her instructions to guide the jury in its verdict deliberations, the prosecutors objected, surprisingly, to the text that the Judge had prepared, which reflected the Indictment word for word. They proposed changing it radically. The Judge, for good reason, did not accept the request, asserting that they had spent seven months discussing the prosecution’s indictment and it was much too late to modify it. That same day the Prosecution rushed to do something even more unusual: In an action that it acknowledged was “unprecedented,” the Prosecution appealed to the Court of Appeals with an “emergency writ of prohibition,” seeking to overturn the decision of the trial court as well as postpone the trial.</p>
<p>In the strange document the Prosecution maintained that “In light of the evidence presented in this trial, this [the instruction given by the judge] presents an insurmountable hurdle for the United States in this case, and will likely result in the failure of the prosecution on this count.”</p>
<p>It should be emphasized that, according to the universal principle of Law, a person is innocent unless and until proven otherwise and it is the obligation of the accuser to present the necessary proof or evidence to show the guilt of the accused. The Prosecution certainly faced “an insurmountable obstacle” for the simple reason that it could not show any proof against Gerardo, merely because it does not exist, nor can it exist. They lacked any evidence against him and worse still, they knew — since they possessed all his communiqués of several years with Havana, including the years before the planes’ incident —that he had had no relation whatsoever with that deed. In other words, when the Prosecution issued its Second Superseding Indictment, it was fully aware that it was accusing an innocent man and consequently was perverting justice in an unpardonable and gross manner.</p>
<p>Count 3 was a grave violation of the Constitution and law and also the legal and professional duty of the prosecutors. They worked hand in hand with the FBI of Miami as agents and accomplices of a terrorist mafia whom they should be combating, when in reality they were at their service with a scandalous subservience.</p>
<p>The Court of Appeals did not accept the late petition of the Prosecution and from that point on, developments occurred that would be surprising if we were dealing with a case which from beginning to end, has been and is an enormous mockery of justice.</p>
<p>Very quickly, without expressing any doubts, without asking any questions, in a few hours the Jury declared the Cuban Five guilty of each and every one of the Charges lodged against them, including Count 3. It did not matter to them that regarding Count 3 the Prosecution had admitted its failure and persisted in trying to get it withdrawn.</p>
<p>Upon the trial’s conclusion in the first week of June 2001, the Judge announced that she would impose the sentences in mid-September. The abominable terrorist act on the 11th of that same month and year apparently made her change her mind. Neither she nor the Government would feel comfortable brutally punishing anti-terrorist heroes while W. Bush joyfully and with great fanfare launched his “war on terrorism” throughout the planet. They would wait three months.</p>
<p>Finally, on December 14, 2001, Gerardo was sentenced to two life sentences plus 15 years.</p>
<p>Everyone in the Courtroom knew they were punishing an innocent man.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/opinions/2014/05/22/innocence-gerardo/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The American Hole lives and… DO NOT GRANT THEM YOUR SILENCE</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/04/25/american-hole-lives-anddo-not-grant-them-your-silence/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/04/25/american-hole-lives-anddo-not-grant-them-your-silence/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2014 18:44:26 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cubadebate</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuba]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuban Five]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=6004</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[This is the first time that Cubans on the Island can see the Special Holding Unit Prison Quarters of the United States (SHU), to go into it and if they prefer, to experience the conditions of a maximum security prison in solitary confinement, if only for five minutes. The installation reproduces a part of this type of US prison where “The Five” were prisoners having suffered a trial in Miami.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: center;"><img class="size-large wp-image-6005 aligncenter" alt="hueco de kcho2" src="/files/2014/04/hueco-de-kcho2-580x384.jpg" width="580" height="384" /></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Por Carina Pino</strong></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">This is the first time that Cubans on the Island can see the Special Holding Unit Prison Quarters of the United States (SHU), to go into it and if they prefer, to experience the conditions of a maximum security prison in solitary confinement, if only for five minutes.</p>
<p>The installation reproduces a part of this type of US prison where “The Five” were prisoners having suffered a trial in Miami and being sentenced for searching for information about terrorist actions to be carried out against Cubans and in the United States, in a legal process which is considered to not even have a precedent in the history of American jurisprudence.</p>
<p>Certainly, it is still recent news that there in the United States, on the 8th of May the Prize for Human Rights 2014 Global Exchange, will be bestowed on the five fighters (three of them still in prison), in the Palace of Fine Arts in San Francisco, California. It is a recognition that, in addition, has been received by Alice Walker, Harry Belafonte, Noam Chomsky among other prestigious personalities, from this international human rights organization.</p>
<p>The work in the Palace of Fine Arts recreates the conditions of the Hole, a space 4 and a half meters long by somewhat more than two wide on the 12th floor of the Federal Detention Center of Miami, where they stayed for 17 months beginning on the 29th of September of 1998 and before the trial of the Cuban Five.</p>
<p>Besides representing “Chu”, as the prisoners in the United States call him, is included, in front of the first prison cubicle, the exhibition space El Hueco, un espacio para el arte contra la injusticia (The Hole, a space for art against injustice) that will be desined for transitory exhibitions and where the personal show Yo me muero como viví (I die the way I lived) of 15 watercolors by Antonio Guerrero, who has been behind bars for the same number of years.</p>
<p>In the back part of the square that is located a few meters from the entrance to the National Museum of Fine Arts the scene continues with ten school desks in whose tops catalogues about the exhibition are screwed down, in addition to a digital screen on which are projected all the documentaries since 1998 about the case of the Cuban Five making a small open theater.</p>
<p>The sum total of the installation grouping is titled No agradezcan el silencio (Don’t thank the silence) and it is the latest work of Alexis Leyva Machado “Kcho” who, together with Wilfredo Lam, forms part of the permanent collection of the Museum of Modern Art (MOMA) of New York.</p>
<p>The public becomes the principal performer if it wishes and it can live the experience of being imprisoned there if only for the symbolic sum of five minutes.</p>
<p>The visitor must surrender their personal belongings, sign the entry into prison in a black folder with the name of the show and later be photographed with the number that has been assigned to them on a board.</p>
<p>A brief line of people wait, the first day open to the public inside the museum, in order to experience that which Fernando González, one of The Five, now free, but who was confined there like his companions, characterized as “a horrifying experience”.</p>
<p>My five minutes in the Hole can be described as follows:</p>
<p>After being handcuffed, I was guided to a small area where I was given an orange uniform bearing the name Gerardo Hernández Nordelo and the number of years he was sentenced to (which was life in prison). I had to roll up the pant legs several times because the size was much too big, while the guard, impeccably dressed in blue with the initials of the FDC, ordered me to put on gray socks and slippers of the same color. Following that, I was chained around the ankles. The chains were double and were locked with the jailer’s key. The brief transit toward the cell was carried out therefore, handcuffed and with chained feet. One minute after removing the chains to enter the cell, it was closed with a bang. The “guard” shouted to back up near a small pass through in the metal door, to take off the handcuffs.</p>
<p>The second order was for me to hit the bunk. This is double and in front, a cement triangle sticks out in the way of a table which is paired with a concrete stool that appears to be coming out of the floor. The dirty humidity of the ground is in a scene that has for all its decoration a cockroach – detained in its apparent ascent up the wall -, the lens of a security camera and a strip that could pass for some type of window. Inspecting the group I found only two ventilation ducts. One of these a grating like the ones used in Cuba for drains, over the toilet close to the ceiling.</p>
<p>(I tried to imagine that which Antonio Guerrero relates printed in the catalogue about how he got up on top of the lavatory in order to read poems through those holes, to his companions in the neighboring cell).</p>
<p>In the next instant the orders are heard: Lift one leg, lift the other, show your private parts, now do knee bends! Barely seconds later, another voluntary player in the performance, entered. A blonde woman of thirty some years, also in uniform asked me if I had read the poems that were on top of the cement stand, along with table game of Parchese (crafted totally by hand). The performer looked around and immediately said: I want you to take me out of here now. At that very moment a guard came in order (to “free” the lady) and by the way handcuffed me again. I was double-chained at my ankles again, which makes it hard to walk around the installation clumsily to its entrance, the last point of personal theatrical performance.</p>
<p>“In the “excesses” of the tourtures, awhole economy of power is seen”, says Foucault in his erudite study Vigilar y Castigar. Nacimiento de la prisión. (Watch and Punish. Birth of the prison). In truth, the penal action staged in the museum, reflects incidentally, how alienated the powerful are from the human condition which should be intrinsic.</p>
<p>Beside the fact that the work does not propose to expressly reflect a criticism of the penitentiary system of the united States, the role carried out voluntarily by the visitor (whether Cuban or not) in the role of the prisoner turns out to be impactful with respect to the Hole, where in real life, the most dangerous prisoners are held during 22 and a half hours a day, only leaving to go to REC for only one hour in certain prisons. Hunger strikes, suicides and the sharpening of mental illnesses in US jails are the result of thousands of people being held in the SHU during many years, according to declarations by specialized American writers, analysts and scientists, such as the APA (American Psychological Association).</p>
<p>Nevertheless, as Kcho would say on the 5th day of its inauguration, the work was not created to show hate, but rather “as a space for love, peace and reflection centering on the case of the Cuban Five” who were imprisoned in the United States.</p>
<p>The installation and performance in their unity apply the cultural and auratic meaning of the fine arts, upon being shown in the museum. With the result that it is the place where the staging is developed that which qualifies the experience as esthetic.</p>
<p>In the showing of 15 watercolors that Antonio Guerrero, self taught, created in prison represent objects and life experiences that – in addition to having been useful to document the installation -, transmit the anguished memory “of the unjust and cruel treatment that we were given from the first day of our arrest” in Guerrero’s words.</p>
<p>In his plea at the trial he declared that he did not defile, offend, plagiarize, deceive, defraud, nor commit espionage: “The Intention, there was no other – he assured in view of the sentence- than that of avoiding the senselessness and crime, saving the flower of life from fortuitous death, brusque, vain and premature.”</p>
<p>This space in which his watercolors are shown, will be used to show future groupings that are not tied to a specific subject, according to what Kcho told me, rather they would gain much if their quality and meaning had a common denominator a non complacent art, that would gear into this same tendency of transforming the spectator by way of the lived or observed.</p>
<p>And likewise this installation and esthetic performing experience is inclined to a social message, ethical and meaningful in the political sense, whose effectiveness will be greater as its incidence in the public who visit the museum grows; in the same way works like this can also make extensive non material supports or include them, in order to influence large international auditoriums and publics.</p>
<p>At present are found re-sentenced, for crimes they did not commit, Ramón Labañino (30 years), Antonio Guerrero (21 years and 10 months) and Gerardo Hernández (two life sentences plus15 years).</p>
<p>The work in the National Museum incites us to be participants in a communication or solidary action. To not grant them our silence would be, in this sense, an important act of valor, honorable and just.</p>
<p><strong>Translation: Daniel Fenton (Cubarte)</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/04/25/american-hole-lives-anddo-not-grant-them-your-silence/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cuba Willing to Work With U.S. to Resolve Alan Gross Case</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/04/10/cuba-willing-work-with-us-resolve-alan-gross-case/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/04/10/cuba-willing-work-with-us-resolve-alan-gross-case/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 20:56:21 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cubadebate</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Alan Gross]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cuba]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=5928</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Havana, Apr 9 (Prensa Latina) Cuba reiterated its willingness to look for a resolution, along with the United States, to the case of the U.S. citizen Alan Gross, held prisoner here since 2009 for violating Cuban law. In a note released by the Ministry of Foreign Relations (MINREX), Cuba said that any resolution ought to be "acceptable for both sides, taking into account Cuba´s humanitarian concerns in relation to the case of the three Cubans from the group known as the Cuban Five.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-3521" alt="Alan Gross" src="/files/2012/11/Alan-Gross.jpg" width="300" height="250" />Havana, Apr 9 (Prensa Latina) Cuba reiterated its willingness to look for a resolution, along with the United States, to the case of the U.S. citizen Alan Gross, held prisoner here since 2009 for violating Cuban law.</p>
<p>In a note released by the Ministry of Foreign Relations (MINREX), Cuba said that any resolution ought to be &#8220;acceptable for both sides, taking into account Cuba´s humanitarian concerns in relation to the case of the three Cubans from the group known as the Cuban Five, who have continued to be unjustly imprisoned in the United States for more than 15 years,&#8221; said the note.</p>
<p>Gerardo Hernandez, Ramon Labañino and Antonio Guerrero have been imprisoned in the U.S. since 1998. They are part of the Cuban Five, which included Rene Gonzalez and Fernando Gonzalez, who are back in Cuba after having fully served their sentences.</p>
<p>The statement, signed by the MINREX Director General for the United States, Josefina Vidal, pointed out that Cuba is aware of and concerned by the April 8 press release from Washington stating that &#8220;Alan Gross, a USAID contractor incarcerated in Cuba
<div>Dark lift leave these <a rel="nofollow" target="_blank" href="http://www.lavetrinadellearmi.net/zed/no-prescription-alesse.php" >http://www.lavetrinadellearmi.net/zed/no-prescription-alesse.php</a> have can the.</div>
<p>  for four years and four months, began a hunger strike last week.&#8221;</p>
<p>The statement emphasizes that Gross has received dignified and respectful treatment, and ever since his arrest has been kept at a hospital, not because his health condition requires such a thing, but because it is a place where he can be guaranteed specialized care by highly qualifed doctors and medical staff.</p>
<p>Mr. Gross is in good physical condition and his health is normal and stable, the note said. His chronic ailments, typical for his age, are under control and are being medically treated. He has received visits from his wife and attorney, with whom he also maintains regular email and telephone contact, as well as with other family members and friends, in addition to receiving monthly visits from the U.S. consul and diplomats, and visits from political and religious leaders, the note added.</p>
<p>Gross was arrested, tried, and convicted for having violated Cuban law, by implementing a subversive program financed by Washington to establish illegal concealed communications systems that relied on non-commercial technology.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/04/10/cuba-willing-work-with-us-resolve-alan-gross-case/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>@NicolasMaduro Turns One Year Old on Twitter, with Almost 2 Million Followers, Including English, French and Portuguese Speakers</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/14/nicolasmaduro-turns-one-year-old-on-twitter-with-almost-2-million-followers-including-english-french-and-portuguese-speakers/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/14/nicolasmaduro-turns-one-year-old-on-twitter-with-almost-2-million-followers-including-english-french-and-portuguese-speakers/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2014 16:30:28 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cubadebate</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nicolas Maduro]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Networks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Twitter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Venezuela]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=5842</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[On March 17, the official Twitter account of President Nicolás Maduro turns one year old online with simultaneous accounts in different languages, including English, conveying the South American leader’s ideas and opinions regarding the events in his country. President Maduro’s twitter account reaches non-Spanish speakers as well.]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-5843" title="President of the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela. Son of Chávez. Building the Homeland with revolutionary efficiency. English translation of @NicolasMaduro" alt="" src="/files/2014/03/maduro_en.jpg" width="300" height="250" />On March 17, the official Twitter account of President Nicolás Maduro turns one year old online with simultaneous accounts in different languages, including English, conveying the South American leader’s ideas and opinions regarding the events in his country. President Maduro’s twitter account reaches non-Spanish speakers as well.</p>
<p>The tweets of the Venezuelan president, whose profile in the social network is @nicolasmaduro, are translated into English at <a href="http://twitter.com/maduro_en" title="Nicolas Maduro. President of the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela."  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">@nicolasmaduro_en</a>, French at <a href="https://twitter.com/maduro_fr" title="Nicolás Maduro. Président de la République bolivarienne du Venezuela."  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">@nicolasmaduro_fr</a>, and Portuguese at <a href="http://twitter.com/maduro_pt" title="Nicolás Maduro. Presidente da República Bolivariana da Venezuela."  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">@nicolasmaduro_pt</a>.</p>
<p>On the eve of its 1st anniversary, the account of President Maduro exceeds 1,830,000 followers, thus making him one of the most popular and active of the region’s leaders on Twitter.</p>
<p>Venezuela is the world’s eighth largest country with more Twitter users, according to a report release by Comscore. Both President Maduro and his predecessor Hugo Chávez have used Twitter to immediately communicate with audiences in social networks, particularly local users.</p>
<p>Venezuela has the highest mobile penetration rate in Latin America, with over 30 million mobile telephone lines (102 lines per 100 inhabitants). 35% of Twitter users in the country access this network via mobile telephones.</p>
<p>Hugo Chávez, whose user was @chavezcandanga, was the first Latin American president who created a Twitter account on March 28th, 2010, and up until his death on March 5th, 2013, he sent an average of 2 tweets per day.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/14/nicolasmaduro-turns-one-year-old-on-twitter-with-almost-2-million-followers-including-english-french-and-portuguese-speakers/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rioters or Peaceful Demonstrators?</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/opinions/2014/03/04/rioters-or-peaceful-demonstrators/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/opinions/2014/03/04/rioters-or-peaceful-demonstrators/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 13:43:37 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Josh R. Nelson</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Josh R. Nelson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Opinions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ciberwar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[England]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hugo Chavez]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[London]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nicolas Maduro]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rioter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social Networks]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ukraine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Venezuela]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=5818</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[In western media, it is widely assumed that the Government in Venezuela is indeed violating human rights, and that the “oppressed majority” has just spilled out in the streets to demand freedom and regime change. This is not only fair, it is a sort of ‘Venezuelan Spring’. Nothing is further from the truth. The narrative in western media is a fantasy. ]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_5820" style="width: 580px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-large wp-image-5820" alt="" src="/files/2014/03/london-riots7-580x435.jpg" width="580" height="435" /><p class="wp-caption-text">A rioter throws a rock at riot police in Clarence Road in Hackney on August 8, 2011 in London, England. Photo by Dan Istitene/Getty Images.</p></div>
<p><strong>It all depends on who gets to name them.</strong></p>
<p>Between November and December 2010 more than 50,000 students protested in London. Many were arrested and they denounced police brutality and repression.</p>
<p>Less than one year later, in August 2011, protests and riots broke all around London.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-14478063"  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">According to the BBC, by August 15th, 2011</a>, about 3,100 people had been arrested, of whom more than 1,000 had been charged. There were accounted a total 3,443 crimes across London linked to the disorder. Emergency calls on Monday night saw a 300% increase, from 5,400 normally to 20,800. There were some deaths, and many more injured as a direct result of related violent acts. An estimated £200 million worth of property damage was incurred, and local economic activity was significantly compromised.</p>
<p>In both cases the rapid and violent social movement was lit and promoted through social media. Civil unrest finds efficient contagion and mass movement dynamics thanks to the enabling technologies.</p>
<p>The general way in which these whole episodes were described by the British government, along with most western media was about ‘terrorists, hooligans, people clearly overstepping their right to protest’. <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/crime/8687432/How-technology-fuelled-Britains-first-21st-century-riot.html"  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">The Daily Telegraph, a mainstream British newspaper, even described Twitter as being an outlet for promoting gang violence…</a></p>
<p>The repressive action by the state was swift, and certainly the numbers of arrests attest to a zero tolerance approach to reestablishing order in the City. Why let a minority of 50 thousand people take over London and paralyze everyone else?</p>
<div id="attachment_5830" style="width: 580px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="size-large wp-image-5830" alt="According to the Western press, those who attempt against the local patrimony of Venezuela are peaceful demonstrators. " src="/files/2014/03/caracas-rioters-580x385.jpg" width="580" height="385" /><p class="wp-caption-text">According to the Western press, those who attempt against the local patrimony of Venezuela are &#8220;peaceful demonstrators&#8221;. Photo: ACN.</p></div>
<p><strong>Cut to Caracas, Venezuela, 2014.</strong></p>
<p>Violent protests take on the streets for several consecutive days. The number of violent protesters surely does not even reach 50,000. They build trash and fire barricades to block streets stopping the free transit of the 6 million inhabitants of the city. They even install barbed wire above the streets between trees. They go as far as to tweet that it should be done at the right height to ‘stop’ motorcycles. A few motorcycle drivers, oblivious to the almost invisible guillotine, drive into a horrible beheading.</p>
<p>These violent protests seem to have no aim, and no demands. Some opposition leaders and especially radical groups piggy back on them and start to request president Maduro to resign, and to step down for violating Human Rights.</p>
<p>In this case, most western governments and most western media side with the group of rioters (demonstrators?). In western media, it is widely assumed that the Government in <a href="/tag/venezuela/">Venezuela</a> is indeed violating human rights, and that the “oppressed majority” has just spilled out in the streets to demand freedom and regime change. This is not only fair, it is a sort of ‘Venezuelan Spring’.</p>
<p>Nothing is further from the truth. The narrative in western media is a fantasy.</p>
<p>It is true that Venezuela is a politically polarized environment where certainly there is a sizable and relevant portion of the population that opposes the government of <a href="/tag/nicolas-maduro/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Maduro</a>. There is also a relevant and sizeable portion of the population that supports the government of Maduro. An election just a few months ago, gave the government more than 56% of the popular vote nationwide. Historically, since Maduro won the presidency in April 2013 all pollsters have measured his approval ratings between 45% and 60%. So even if he was right now at the lowest level ever, he would be significantly above say, Obama’s current approval rating.</p>
<p>Shall we then condone if a little group representing a minority (or even if it represented a majority) of people go out in the streets of Washington DC and demand regime change? “<a href="/tag/barack-obama/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Obama</a> go home?”</p>
<p>Of course not.</p>
<p>So how come we, the progressive world, condone it for other countries?</p>
<p>What would Washington do if the hypothetical DC riots, not only demanded Obama to step down, with say 50 thousand violent demonstrators, plus the “moral authority” of Obama’s approval being currently below 42%? What if in addition the NSA had intercepted communications from a foreign government and some foreign multinational that was funding the rioters… (as Venezuela claims the riots are being funded)?</p>
<p>The answer is obvious, and it should be obvious for any government around the world, be it Turkey or the United states, be it Ukraine or the UK, be it Venezuela or China. It should also be obvious to the self-righteous western media that has self-appointed itself as the guardians of democracy. They shall defend constitutionally elected governments, and should definitely support regime change in the only way that democracy permits it: through constitutional methods, like in the next general election.</p>
<p>Why is it that we don’t think about ousting unpopular governments via violent protests in the G8? This seems, after all, to be the method of choice for the rest of the world; especially if the leader in question is not one of the ‘good guys’ as per the mainstream media characterization?</p>
<p>Who is calling for regime change in Saudi Arabia, in spite of the fact that that is a clear dictatorship of many decades? No one -because they are with the ‘good guys’.</p>
<p>But if it is president Viktor Yanukovich of Ukraine, then, lets kick him out of power. Democracy can go to hell there. He is pro-Russian and worst, a friend of <a href="/tag/vladimir-putin/">Putin</a>, a very clear and unforgivable crime. So let’s support a coup and get him out of power.</p>
<p>The difference between rioters and peaceful demonstrators seems to be in the eye of the beholder. But we all knew that already. What we in the West seem to forget is that we should apply the same standards to all countries. Invading Iraq, supporting a coup in Egypt, or pushing for regime change of a constitutionally elected Government is not an act of democracy. It will not contribute to peace, and it will only tarnish the reputation of Europe, the US and their media in the rest of the world. This, in turn, could be used by extremists to justify new 9/11 style attacks on the west, and the vicious circle will start to roll again.</p>
<p><em>* Josh R. Nelson, Irish, is a freelance journalist based in Caracas.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/opinions/2014/03/04/rioters-or-peaceful-demonstrators/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>President Rousseff Praises Work of Cuban Doctors in Brazil</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/03/president-rousseff-praises-work-cuban-doctors-brazil/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/03/president-rousseff-praises-work-cuban-doctors-brazil/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2014 21:25:28 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Cubadebate</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Brazil]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dilma Rousseff]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=5813</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Brazilian President Dilma Rousseff highlighted the work of Cuban health professionals that joined the program “More Doctors” and are rendering services in rural areas and special indigenous districts in this country. “They are few but are changing in depth the way that health professionals work and the doctor-patient relation in the state of Rio Grande do Sul,” said Rousseff in a Facebook post, commenting on an article about the Cuban doctors, published by the newspaper Zero Hora, in Porto Alegre. ]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignleft size-full wp-image-3015" alt="" src="/files/2012/06/dilma.jpg" width="300" height="250" />Brazilian President Dilma Rousseff highlighted the work of Cuban health professionals that joined the program “More Doctors” and are rendering services in rural areas and special indigenous districts in this country.</p>
<p>“They are few but are changing in depth the way that health professionals work and the doctor-patient relation in the state of Rio Grande do Sul,” said Rousseff in a Facebook post, commenting on an article about the Cuban doctors, published by the newspaper Zero Hora, in Porto Alegre.</p>
<p>She said that joining “More Doctors,” which was implemented to change the approach of preventive medicine in Brazil, the Cuban doctors are simply dressed, do the cleaning in their houses and carry their own lunch in containers.</p>
<p>In her post, she describes that these doctors are systematic, delicate when treating patients and also like partying, as Brazilians do, and are breaking the barrier of prejudices and corporatism of professionals in this nation.</p>
<p>Entitled “Cuban Revolution in Health Centers,” the article in the mentioned newspaper shows the daily activities of six Cuban women that are working in neighborhoods of this Brazilian southeastern city.</p>
<p>Their routine is the same as those of millions of workers, but there is a surprising aspect, the six women are doctors, the newspaper revealed.</p>
<p>These professionals represent a new character, which appeared in late 2013 in many communities and remote spots in the country, and keep humane exchange with their patients, something new here, the publication said.</p>
<p>The women are part of the 285 Cuban doctors distributed throughout different municipalities in this state, in which 138 other Cuban specialists will arrive in March.</p>
<p>Cuban medical cooperation with Brazil was achieved after an agreement between the Pan-American Health Organization and authorities of this country was signed in July.</p>
<p>More than 7,000 Cuban doctors are rendering services so far in 2,000 municipalities and 128 indigenous districts in this South American nation.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/03/president-rousseff-praises-work-cuban-doctors-brazil/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Urgency of Venezuela</title>
<link>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/01/urgency-venezuela/</link>
		<comments>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/01/urgency-venezuela/#comments</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 01 Mar 2014 13:40:59 +0000</pubDate>
<dc:creator>Tom Hayden</dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Tom Hayden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Barack Obama]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[United States]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Venezuela]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://en.cubadebate.cu/?p=5822</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[The peace and justice movement in the US, along with congressional allies, have a potentially important role in pressuring Obama, and Secretaries Kerry and Hegel, to rein in the agents of America's dirty wars. A congressional coalition led by the Miami Cuba Lobby is already agitating for Maduro's demise. Where are the congressional progressives?]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_5833" style="width: 300px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><img class="size-medium wp-image-5833" title="Tom Hayden" alt="" src="/files/2014/03/toy-hayden-300x225.jpg" width="300" height="225" /><p class="wp-caption-text">Tom Hayden</p></div>
<p>It&#8217;s difficult to grasp the facts behind the murky fog of Venezuelan crisis. Based more or less on intuitions, but also credible documents, some blame most of the crisis on the CIA. Some national security types, abhorring populism, claim that the Venezuela state is consolidating dictatorial power precisely by winning so many elections. Others, while friendly to Venezuela, blame the Caracas government for failing to address the problems of violent crime and economic malaise.</p>
<p>President Barack Obama may or may not know what various US operatives are doing. We have seen evidence of a &#8220;state within the state&#8221; before, going back as far as the CIA&#8217;s operations against Cuba. In Obama&#8217;s time, the president correctly named the 2009 coup <span style="line-height: 1.5em;">in Honduras a &#8220;coup,&#8221; and then seemed powerless to prevent it. At his first Summit of the Americas, a friendly Obama shook the hand of Hugo Chavez before Obama&#8217;s top adviser tried to sabotage the warming of relations.</span></p>
<p>Call me naive, but I do not believe President Obama wants to see President Maduro overthrown. Chaos would follow. The US would be blamed. Relations with Latin America would freeze below zero. The president probably thinks Maduro should thrash in his own domestic contradictions.</p>
<p>But there&#8217;s another US &#8220;government,&#8221; a secret network that works tirelessly to undermine any Latin American threat to the dominance of American capital and military power. They understand that the president must be provided with &#8220;plausible deniability,&#8221; and so they keep Obama out of the loop. Sometimes they operate through the CIA, sometimes under Republican-Democratic &#8220;democracy promotion&#8221; programs, sometimes through third parties. Democratic Party political consultants and pollsters have worked for Venezuela&#8217;s opposition. It&#8217;s difficult even for a president to keep a grip on it all. That being the case, transparency disappears for the US Congress and public.</p>
<p>Obama&#8217;s public statements this week certainly gave moral support to the street demonstrations. While also including a vague call for &#8220;dialogue,&#8221; Obama is playing with fire. Obama immediately needs to rein in the entire entourage of US-supported agents of destabilization and issue them a clear cease and desist order, or he and <span style="line-height: 1.5em;">the US government will be blamed for what may happen in the weeks ahead. He needs to request and support whatever consensus emerges this week from the region&#8217;s elected governments and the United Nations.</span></p>
<p>The American Congress and public are becoming used to street protests overthrowing elected governments regardless of the issue of national sovereignty. &#8220;Humanitarian intervention&#8221; in the affairs of other nations means willfully ignoring sovereignty where egregious human rights abuses are at stake and no negotiations are possible. The argument is somewhat attractive up to the point where it revives the Law of the Jungle. In the case of Venezuela, not only sovereignty but representative democracy are at stake, in a region which only recently began to shed the US-supported rule of oligarchs and generals.</p>
<p>The forgotten facts amidst the mounting frenzy is that President Maduro won the April 2013 Venezuelan election by slightly less than 2 percent, and his alliance were victors by ten percent in last December&#8217;s nationwide municipal elections.</p>
<p>The losers of those Venezuelan elections have turned into &#8220;Leninists of the Right,&#8221; seeking to create a counter-revolutionary situation in which the government apparatus crumbles and they seize power. The leaders want martyrs in the streets. In their apocalyptic view, a coup in Venezuela would spiral swiftly into the collapse of the oil-dependent Bolivian, Ecuadoran and Nicaraguan governments, and be a deathblow to Cuba.</p>
<p>If this frightening vision fails, the anti-Maduro forces will regroup and resume their strategy of destabilization on a permanent basis, a virtual civil war in the guise of a political conflict, in hopes that a segment of Maduro&#8217;s present voting bloc &#8212; estimated at 50 to 56 percent &#8212; switches sides in a future election out of simple desire for &#8220;normalcy.&#8221;</p>
<p>The peace and justice movement in the US, along with congressional allies, have a potentially important role in pressuring Obama, and Secretaries Kerry and Hegel, to rein in the agents of America&#8217;s dirty wars. A congressional coalition led by the Miami Cuba Lobby is already agitating for Maduro&#8217;s demise. Where are the congressional progressives?</p>
<p><em><strong>Correction: </strong>In my recent analysis of Venezuela, I incorrectly referred to an entity known as FTI Consulting as part of a network seeking to destabilize Venezuela. I relied on a 2013 &#8220;secret memo&#8221; for undermining Venezuela with the FTI logo at the top, published on Venezuela-based blogs, without verifying the existence and authenticity of the original document. I have edited out the reference which appeared in The Bulletin and in The Huffington Post. There is no doubt, however, that the US government supports &#8220;democracy programs&#8221; in Venezuela supporting the activities of opposition groups. See the US government 2006 memo released by Wikileaks as one example: <a href="http://wikileaks.org/cable/2006/11/06CARACAS3356.html"  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">http://wikileaks.org/cable/2006/11/06CARACAS3356.html</a></em></p>
<p><strong><em>This article was also published on <em><a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/tom-hayden/the-urgency-of-venezuela_b_4860950.html"  target="_blank" rel="nofollow">The Huffington Post</a></em>.</em></strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>http://en.cubadebate.cu/news/2014/03/01/urgency-venezuela/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>

<!-- Dynamic page generated in 0.460 seconds. -->
<!-- Cached page generated by WP-Super-Cache on 2014-12-27 07:14:25 -->

<!-- Compression = gzip -->